<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: STEM | Webjitsu]]></title>
  <link href="http://xharekx33.github.io/blog/categories/stem/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://xharekx33.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2019-04-16T18:18:06+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://xharekx33.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Harek]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[xharekx33@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How NOT to get women in tech]]></title>
    <link href="http://xharekx33.github.io/blog/2019/04/16/how-to-not-get-women-in-tech/"/>
    <updated>2019-04-16T17:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://xharekx33.github.io/blog/2019/04/16/how-to-not-get-women-in-tech</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It&rsquo;s no secret that tech is largely a boys club. Predominantly a <strong>white</strong> boys club. We could most definitely do with more diversity in all fronts: more women, more people of color, more age groups, etc.</p>

<p>But please, please, if you or your company want to address this issue, don&rsquo;t just do it to cash in by jumping into the bandwagon. And even if that is your ultimate reason, please try and do a good job about it so your insincerity is not so <strong>painfully obvious</strong>.</p>

<p>What do I mean? I mean that if you want to name examples of notable women in tech or science to inpire young girls, <strong>don&rsquo;t be so damn lazy</strong> and pick more recent and relevant examples than <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ada_Lovelace">Ada Lovelace</a>.</p>

<p>Yes, Ada&rsquo;s story is fundamental and inspiring, but a high school girl in 2019 reading about how STEM is not just for boys, and having the only example be a <strong>19th century mathematician</strong>, is most likely only gonna be bummed about the whole thing.</p>

<p>There&rsquo;s plenty of women to choose from, for whom we have actual <strong>photographs</strong> to go along the text, instead of oil paintings: <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Margaret_Hamilton_(scientist">Margaret Hamilton</a>), <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Katherine_Johnson">Katherine Johnson</a>, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Susan_Kare">Susan Kare</a> or <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Megan_Smith">Megan Smith</a> to name just a few. Hell, these past few days just gave us the amazing <a href="https://www.cbsnews.com/news/katie-bouman-black-hole-image-algorithm-mit/">Katie Bouman</a>. I&rsquo;d bet it&rsquo;s hard to get a more fitting example to get young girls into science today.</p>

<p>All it takes is a little time and will to do it right.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
